afp.gov.au 2019-12-09

# Privacy | Australian Federal Police

The Australian Federal Police is subject to the Australian Privacy Principles (APPs) at Schedule 1 of the _Privacy Act 1988_ (Cth) (Privacy Act).

The AFP has a Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB) that explains how the AFP complies with the Privacy Act and the APPs.

## The purposes for which the AFP collects, holds, uses and discloses personal information

The AFP collects, holds, uses and discloses personal information for purposes which are directly related to our functions or activities as set out in section 8 of the _Australian Federal Police Act 1979_ (Cth) (AFP Act) and the Ministerial Direction, and only when it is necessary or directly related to such purposes.

For a detailed explanation of these purposes refer to section 4 of the AFP Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB).

## Collection of personal information

The AFP collects and holds a range of personal information in connection with our functions, including:

  * licensing records
  * administrative records
  * records that assist in the enforcement of the criminal law, preservation of peace, the prevention, detection and investigation of criminal incidents, the protection of life, safety and property
  * investigation records
  * intelligence records
  * court records
  * criminal records
  * professional standards records
  * traffic records
  * illicit drug testing records
  * records relating to forensic procedures
  * personnel records
  * coronial investigation records.

The AFP collects personal information from a variety of sources including:

  * you or someone representing you
  * a third party
  * another APP entity
  * a publicly available source
  * a Commonwealth, state or territory security, intelligence or government agency
  * a state or territory police force
  * a foreign law enforcement, security, intelligence or government agency
  * a court or tribunal
  * a royal commission
  * the Commonwealth, state or territory Director of Public Prosecutions.

The AFP may also collect personal information or sensitive information about you by utilising legislative provisions.

Detailed information about the type of personal information that the AFP collects is set out at section 5 of the AFP Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB).

## Handling, storage and protection of personal information

All records are handled and stored in accordance with the requirements of the _Archives Act 1983_ (Cth), AFP Records Authority issued by the National Archives and the Australian Government Protective Security Policy Framework.

For further information on the handling and storage of personal information refer to sections 5(d) and (e) of the AFP Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB).

## Use and disclosure of personal information

The AFP only uses and discloses personal information for:

  * the purposes for which it was collected
  * purposes permitted by legislation
  * for purposes which are directly related to the AFP's functions as contained in the AFP Act and the Ministerial Direction
  * in accordance with the provisions contained in section 60A of the AFP Act and the AFP Regulations.

The AFP does not provide your personal information to other Australian or foreign law enforcement, intelligence, security or government agencies, organisations or individuals unless the disclosure is authorised by the AFP Act and the Privacy Act, or is otherwise required or authorised by law.

### Disclosure of personal information overseas

The AFP is authorised to cooperate with, and provide assistance to, foreign law enforcement, intelligence and security agencies in accordance with the AFP Act and the Ministerial Direction.

The AFP may also disclose personal information overseas in accordance with legislation and a number of treaties.

For more information on the use and disclosure of personal information refer to section 6 of the AFP Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB).

## Access to personal information

You have a right to access your personal information under the Privacy Act. Requests for access will be permitted unless there is a sound reason under relevant Australian law to withhold the information.

The AFP will respond in writing to your request within 30 days of receipt.

Requests can be made in writing to:

Post | 

Privacy Officer  
AFP Legal  
Australian Federal Police  
GPO Box 401  
Canberra ACT 2601  
  
---|---  
Email | [privacy@afp.gov.au](mailto:privacy@afp.gov.au)  
  
For further information on accessing personal information see section 7(a) of the AFP Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB).

## Correction of personal information

You have the right to request a correction of your personal information under the Privacy Act. The AFP is required to make the corrections to your personal information if it is reasonable to do so.

The AFP will respond in writing to your request within 30 days of receipt.

Requests can be made in writing to:

Post | 

Privacy Officer  
AFP Legal  
Australian Federal Police  
GPO Box 401  
Canberra ACT 2601  
  
---|---  
Email | [privacy@afp.gov.au](mailto:privacy@afp.gov.au)  
  
For additional information on correcting personal information refer to section 8 of the AFP Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB).

## Privacy complaints

If you are unhappy with the way the AFP has handled your personal information you can lodge a complaint with the AFP's Privacy Officer.

Privacy complaints may be investigated in cooperation with the AFP's Professional Standards area, depending upon the issues raised by the complaint.

For more information on how the AFP handles privacy complaints refer to section 9 of the AFP Privacy Policy (PDF, 90KB).

How to contact the AFP's Privacy Contact Officer:

Telephone | (02) 6131 6131  
---|---  
Post | Privacy Officer  
AFP Legal  
GPO Box 401  
Canberra ACT 2601  
Email | [privacy@afp.gov.au](mailto:privacy@afp.gov.au)  
  
You may also refer your complaint to the Office of the Australian Information Commissioner.

Telephone | 1300 363 992  
---|---  
TTY | 1800 620 241  
Post | Office of the Australian Information Commissioner  
GPO Box 5218  
Sydney NSW 2001  
Facsimile | +61 2 9284 9666  
Website | [www.oaic.gov.au](http://www.oaic.gov.au/)
